<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on Mathias Unberath</title>
    <link>https://mathiasunberath.github.io/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on Mathias Unberath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mathiasunberath.github.io/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Magic Mirror for Facial Anatomy Tracking</title>
      <link>https://mathiasunberath.github.io/project/delta_derma/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathiasunberath.github.io/project/delta_derma/</guid>
      <description>Significance: Anatomy is one of the most challenging subject matters to both teach and learn, and facial anatomy is one of the most complex anatomical regions. Current education relies heavily on cadaveric dissection, supplemented by textbooks; however, human cadavers are expensive and limited in availability, and reading textbooks can feel like a chore to some students. Augmented reality (AR) has the potential to transform the process of learning human anatomy. By blending real and virtual objects, AR allows learners to immerse themselves in the subject matter and take an active role in the learning process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Educating Surgeons in Complex Pelvic Trauma</title>
      <link>https://mathiasunberath.github.io/project/delta_ortho/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathiasunberath.github.io/project/delta_ortho/</guid>
      <description>Significance: Treatment of unstable pelvic fractures relies on open reduction followed by internal fixation using surgical plates and screws, a surgery only performed by highly experienced and well-trained surgeons due to the complexity of the pelvic anatomy. The key challenge is the mental mapping of plate positioning and screw trajectories to the fractured anatomy in 3D, a skill that surgeons in training cannot easily acquire from conventional 2D training material such as textbooks, websites, or illustrations from their instructor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>